Guide to the New-York Historical Society Publication Editorial Records 1939-2000, 2009 NYHS-RG 17
New-York Historical Society
- Series II. Publications (1960s-1980)., 1940s-1998 (bulk 1963-1979); 6.25 Linear feet
  - Subseries II.A. Correspondence by Author, 1957-1980; 3.33 Linear feet
    - Hanyan, Craig. "Clinton", 1971-1972 (Offsite-box 16, Folder 7)
      Includes manuscript submission "De Witt Clinton and Partisanship: The Development of Clintonianism from 1811 to 1820."
    - Harmond, Richard. "Ebenezer Sage", 1972-1973 (Offsite-box 16, Folder 8)
    - Harris, Jonathan. "Clinton", 1971-1972 (Offsite-box 16, Folder 9)
      Includes manuscript submission "De Witt Clinton as Naturalist."
    - Hawke, David Freeman. "Young" (2 folders), 1969-1970 (Offsite-box 16, Folder 10-11)
      Includes manuscript submission "Dr. Thomas Young: Eternal Fisher in Troubled Waters."
    - Hay, Robert P. "Fourth of July", 1968-1969 (Offsite-box 16, Folder 12)
      Includes manuscript submission "Britons in New York on Brother Jonathan's Birthday."
    - Hayes, John D. "Halpine", 1965-1968 (Offsite-box 18, Folder 1)
      Includes manuscript submission "Charles Graham Halpine: The Life and Adventures of Miles O'Reilly."
    - Heale, M.J. "Antebellum Reformers", 1970-1971 (Offsite-box 17, Folder 2)
    - Hellman, Geoffrey T. "New Yorker", 1967 (Offsite-box 17, Folder 3)
      Includes manuscript submission "My Life and Times with The New Yorker," which was originally delivered as a lecture at N-YHS on February 7, 1967.
    - Herndon, G. Melvin. "William Tatham", 1973 (Offsite-box 17, Folder 4)
    - Heslin, James J. "Allegania", 1966 (Offsite-box 17, Folder 5)
      Includes manuscript submission "The Republic of Allegania."
    - Jezierski, John V. "Picquet", 1969-1970 (Offsite-box 17, Folder 6)
    - Jones, George Fenwick. "Kirkland", 1969 (Offsite-box 17, Folder 7)
      Includes manuscript submission "Fragment of a Letter by Samuel Kirkland."
    - Jones, Wilbur Devereux. "Made in New York", 1966-1967 (Offsite-box 17, Folder 8)
      Includes manuscript submission "Made in New York: A Plot to Kill the Queen."
    - Judd, Jacob. "Gleanings from a Captain's Letter", 1966-1968 (Offsite-box 17, Folder 9)
      Includes manuscript submission.
    - Judd, Jacob. "Frederick Philipse", 1970-1971 (Offsite-box 17, Folder 10)
      Includes manuscript submission " Frederick Philipse of New York and the Madagascar Trade in the Late 17th Century."
    - Kantor, Harvey A. "City Beautiful", 1971-1973 (Offsite-box 17, Folder 11)
      Includes manuscript submission "The City Beautiful in New York."
    - Katz, Stanley. "Newcastle's New York", 1966-1967 (Offsite-box 17, Folder 12)
      Includes manuscript submission "Newcastle's New York: Imperial Patronage During the Era of 'Salutary Neglect.'"
    - Ketchum, Richard M. "Tarleton Letters", 1966-1967 (Offsite-box 17, Folder 13)
      Includes manuscript submission "New War Letters of Banastre Tarleton."
    - Klebanow, Diana. "Godkin", 1968-1970 (Offsite-box 17, Folder 14)
      Includes manuscript submission "E.L. Godkin, the City, and Civic Responsibility."
    - Knudson, Jerry W. "Thomas Paine", 1968 (Offsite-box 17, Folder 15)
      Includes manuscript submission "The Rage Around Tom Paine: Newspaper Reaction to his Homecoming to New York in 1802."
    - Kupp, Jan. "Dutch Trade", 1971-1975 (Offsite-box 17, Folder 16)
      Includes manuscript submission "Some Aspects of the Dutch Trade in the New York Competition for Canadian Furs, 1670-1674."
    - Kurland, Gerald. "Citizens' Union", 1968-1969 (Offsite-box 17, Folder 17)
      Includes manuscript submission "The Amateur in Politics: The Citizens' Union and the Greater New York Mayoralty Campaign of 1897."
    - Launtz-Schurer, Jr., Leopold S. "De Lanceys", 1971-1972 (Offsite-box 18, Folder 1)
      Includes manuscript submission "The De Lanceys of New York: Whig-Loyalists."
    - Leder, Lawrence H. "Dongan's New York", 1970 (Offsite-box 18, Folder 2)
      Includes manuscript submission "Policy, Politics, and Personalities in Dongan's New York and Fletcher's London."
    - Lockwood, Charles. "Bond Street", 1971-1972 (Offsite-box 18, Folder 3)
      Includes manuscript submission "The Bond Street Area."
    - Lombard, Charles M. "Old New York Salon", 1970 (Offsite-box 18, Folder 4)
      Includes manuscript submission "An Old New York Salon, French Style."
    - Luhrs, Kathleen. "Portraits of New Yorkers", 1974 (Offsite-box 18, Folder 5)
      Includes manuscript submission, co-authored by Wendy Shadwell.
    - Lydon, James G. "Capture of 1744", 1967-1969 (Offsite-box 18, Folder 6)
    - Mason, Bernard. "Carl Becker", 1968-1969 (Offsite-box 18, Folder 7)
    - Matlack, James H. "Alta California", 1973-1974 (Offsite-box 18, Folder 8)
    - McAdams, Donald R. "Sullivan Expedition", 1969-1970 (Offsite-box 18, Folder 9)
      Includes manuscript submission "The Sullivan Expedition: Success or Failure."
    - McDade, Thomas M. "Christian Brown", 1967 (Offsite-box 18, Folder 10)
      Includes manuscript submission "Christian Brown: Wanted for Murder."
    - Mohl, Raymond A. "Urban Reform in Early New York", 1968-1969 (Offsite-box 18, Folder 11)
    - Mohr, James C. "New York State Free School", 1968-1969 (Offsite-box 18, Folder 12)
      Includes manuscript submission "New York State's Free School Law of 1867: A Chapter in the Reconstruction of the North."
    - Mondello, Salvatore. "Vanderlyn", 1966-1967 (Offsite-box 18, Folder 13)
      Includes manuscript submission "John Vanderlyn, 1775-1852."
    - Mount, Charles M. "Gilbert Stuart", 1972, 1974 (Offsite-box 18, Folder 14)
      Includes manuscript submission "'To Secure A Picture of the President': Gilbert Stuart at New York" (not accepted for publication).
    - Muccigrosso, Robert. "City Reform Club", 1967-1968 (Offsite-box 19, Folder 1)
      Includes manuscript submission "The City Reform Club: A Study in Late Nineteenth Century Reform."
    - Mushkat, Jerome. "M.M. Noah", 1970-1971 (Offsite-box 19, Folder 2)
      Includes manuscript submission "Epitaph for an Era: Modecai Noah's Post Mortems."
    - Nelson, Paul David. "Gates/Arnold", 1970-1971 (Offsite-box 19, Folder 3)
      Includes manuscript submission "The Gates-Arnold Quarrel, September 1777."
    - Ogden, F. Clerc. "David Ogden", 1966 (Offsite-box 19, Folder 4)
      Includes manuscript submission of typescript of "An Account of the Voyage of the Ship Kalamazoo from Liverpool to New York, October 1 to December 6, 1844" (not accepted for publication).
    - Oliva, L. Jay. "Maxim Gorky", 1966-1967 (Offsite-box 19, Folder 5)
      Includes manuscript submission "Maxim Gorky Discovers America: The 'Great Vesuvian Eruption' of 1906."
    - Olm, Lee. "Mutiny Act", 1973-1974 (Offsite-box 19, Folder 6)
    - Olson, Gary D. "Soderstrom", 1970-1972 (Offsite-box 19, Folder 7)
      Includes manuscript submission "The Soderstrom Incident: A Reflection Upon Federal-State Relations Under the Articles of Confederation." Includes copies of correspondence from 1950 related to Soderstrom between the American Swedish Historical Foundation and various archival repositories.
    - Parmet, Robert D. "Depew", 1969 (Offsite-box 19, Folder 8)
      Includes manuscript submission "The Presidential Fever of Chauncey Depew."
    - Parsons, Lynn H. "Hamilton", 1966-1968 (Offsite-box 19, Folder 9)
      Includes manuscript submission "Federalism, the British Empire, and Alexander Hamilton."
    - Pessen, Edward. "Wealthy New Yorkers", 1970 (Offsite-box 19, Folder 10)
    - Pessen, Edward. "Jacksonian Brooklyn", 1970-1971 (Offsite-box 19, Folder 11)
      Includes manuscript submission "A Social and Economic Portrait of Jacksonian Brooklyn: Inequality, Social Immobility, and Class Distinction in the Nation's Seventh City."
    - Pessen, Edward. "Philip Hone", 1971-1972 (Offsite-box 19, Folder 12)
      Includes manuscript submission "Philip Hone's Set: The Social Exclusiveness of the New York City Elite in the 'Age of Egalitarianism.'"
    - Pitkin, Thomas M. "Ellis Island", 1967-1969 (Offsite-box 19, Folder 13)
    - Posner, Russell M. "Keating", 1970-1971 (Offsite-box 19, Folder 14)
      Includes manuscript submission "An English Tour of New York in 1830."
    - Rainbolt, John C. "Bellomont", 1969 (Offsite-box 19, Folder 15)
      Includes manuscript submission "Lord Bellomont's Proposal for New York, 1698-1701."
    - Rainbolt, John C. "Governor & Capt. General", 1972-1973 (Offsite-box 19, Folder 16)
      Includes manuscript submission "The Creation of a Governor and Captain General for the Northern Colonies: The Process of Colonial Policy Formation at the End of the Seventeenth Century."
    - Reeves, Thomas C. "Silas Burt/Chester Arthur", 1970 (Offsite-box 20, Folder 1)
    - Richards, Pamela Spence. "NYHS Library" (2 folders), 1979-1980 (Offsite-box 20, Folder 2-3)
      Concerns N-YHS's plans, which did not go through, to publish Richards's history of the N-YHS Library, Scholars and Gentleman. Folders include printing cost estimates and an incomplete copy of Richards's manuscript.
    - Ritchie, Carson I.A. "Pattison Diary", 1963-1968 (Offsite-box 20, Folder 4)
    - Ritchie, Donald A. "Gary Committee", 1972-1973 (Offsite-box 20, Folder 5)
    - Ritchie, Robert C. "Duke of York", 1973-1974 (Offsite-box 20, Folder 6)
    - Rodechko, James P. "Michael J. O'Brien: Irish-American Historian", 1968-1970 (Offsite-box 20, Folder 7)
    - Rooney, Gerald F. "Daniel Denton", 1968-1971 (Offsite-box 20, Folder 8)
    - Roper, Donald. "Smith Thompson", 1966-1967 (Offsite-box 20, Folder 9)
      Includes manuscript submission "Politics and the New York Supreme Court in the Early Nineteenth Century: Justice Smith Thompson."
    - Roper, Donald R. "James Kent", 1971-1972 (Offsite-box 20, Folder 10)
      Includes manuscript submission "The Elite of the New York Bar as seen from the Bench: James Kent's Necrologies."
    - Runte, Alfred. "Niagara Falls", 1972-1973 (Offsite-box 20, Folder 11)
      Includes manuscript submission "Beyond the Spectacular: The Niagara Falls Preservation Campaign."
    - Scanlon, James E. "Robert Hunter", 1972-1973 (Offsite-box 20, Folder 12)
      Includes manuscript submission "British Intrigue and the Governorship of Robert Hunter."
    - Scott, Kenneth. "Kingston Gaol", 1967-1968 (Offsite-box 20, Folder 13)
      Includes manuscript submission "LIberties of the Kingston Gaol."
    - Seraile, William. "Black Regiments in New York State", 1973-1974 (Offsite-box 20, Folder 14)
    - Shammas, Carole. "Cadwallader Colden", 1968-1969 (Offsite-box 20, Folder 15)
    - Sharrow, Walter G. "Northern Catholic Intellectuals", 1973 (Offsite-box 20, Folder 16)
    - Simon, Donald E. "Brooklyn Election, 1860", 1966-1967 (Offsite-box 20, Folder 17)
    - Skeen, C. Edward. "James Armstrong & John Monroe", 1972-1973 (Offsite-box 20, Folder 18)
      Includes manuscript submission "Monroe and Armstrong: A Study in Political Rivalry."
    - Skolnick, Richard. "G.E. Waring, Jr.", 1967-1968 (Offsite-box 25, Folder 1)
    - Smith, Helen Burr. "IB Silversmith", 1966-1968 (Offsite-box 21, Folder 2)
      Includes manuscript submission "A New IB Silversmith and Two Unrecorded Pewterers."
    - Smith, Mary Ann. "Marble Palace", 1972-1974 (Offsite-box 21, Folder 3)
    - Spencer, Donald S. "Genet", 1969-1972 (Offsite-box 21, Folder 4)
    - Stehle, R.L. "Dusseldorf Gallery", 1974 (Offsite-box 21, Folder 5)
      Includes manuscript submission "The Dusseldorf Gallery of New York."
    - Stein, Judith. "Kenneth Simpson", 1971 (Offsite-box 21, Folder 6)
      Includes manuscript submission "The Impact of the New Deal on New York Politics: Kenneth Simpson and the Republican Party."
    - Stephens, A. Ray. "Doubleday", 1968-1972 (Offsite-box 21, Folder 7)
      Concerns preliminary arrangements for the possible publication of Abner Doubleday's Mexican War journal.
    - Stern, Steve J. "Knickerbockers", 1972-1974 (Offsite-box 21, Folder 8)
    - Strickland, J.E. "Journal of a Tour in the U.S.", 1957-1976 (Offsite-box 21, Folder 9)
    - Syrett, David. "Rodney", 1975-1980 (Offsite-box 21, Folder 10)
      Concerns preparations, cancelled in 1980, for publication of the Order Book of Admiral Lord Rodney.
    - Trattner, Walter I. "Schuyler", 1966-1967 (Offsite-box 21, Folder 11)
      Includes manuscript submission "Louisa Lee Schuyler and the Founding of the New York State Charities Aid Association."
    - Vail, R.W.G. "Land Promotion", 1966-1968 (Offsite-box 21, Folder 12)
      Concerns Mrs. Vail's interest in publishing her late husband's article with N-YHS. This was unsuccessful and the article was eventually published in the University of Rochester Library's Bulletin.
    - Warner, Lee H. "Silver Grays", 1972-1973 (Offsite-box 21, Folder 13)
    - Webster, T.S. "Thorn", 1967-1969 (Offsite-box 21, Folder 14)
      Includes manuscript submission "A Young New Yorker in the French Revolution."
    - Wells, Robert V. "New York Census of 1731", 1972-1973 (Offsite-box 21, Folder 15)
    - Wennersten, John R. "Godwin", 1974-1976 (Offsite-box 21, Folder 16)
      Includes manuscript submission "Slavery, Socialism, and the Anti-Abolition Reformer: A Case Study of Parke Godwin, 1840-1848."
    - Wright, Langdon G. "New Netherland", 1971-1972 (Offsite-box 21, Folder 17)
      Includes manuscript submission "Local Government and Central Authority in New Netherland."
  - Subseries II.B. Other Correspondence and Work Files, 1940s-1998 (bulk, 1963-1979); 2.92 Linear feet
    The subseries is arranged by document type and topically within document type. Files that primarily include correspondence appear first, followed by work files of editorial, administrative, and other matters.
    This subseries includes correspondence other than that with authors of Quarterly articles (which is found above in subseries II.A). This correspondence primarily concerns the production aspects of the Quarterly, including design, printing, and publicity. Accordingly, the principal correspondents are vendors providing production services to N-YHS, including designer Klaus Gemming, Finn Typographers, and Meriden Gravure Company. There is some correspondence concerning Quarterly content, including solicitations for book reviewers and commentary from the Publications Committee. And there is some correspondence related to matters other than the Quarterly, such as with University Press of Virginia concerning distribution of N-YHS's publications. There is also continuing correspondence, primarily from the late 1960s and 1970s, transmitting inquiries and information relevant to a potential update to the Dictionary of Artists in America (see series I.A for similar correspondence from prior to 1966).
    In addition to correspondence, the subseries includes various work files related to editorial and administrative matters. Most of these files include edited submissions and galley proofs for the Quarterly's book reviews and for N-YHS's Annual Report. The work files also include notes on the Editorial Department's production expense budget from the mid-1960s to mid-1970s, along with the billings from its service providers for this period.
    - Correspondence. General (2 folders), 1967-1978 (Offsite-box 22, Folder 1-2)
    - Correspondence. Proposed Articles (2 folders), 1966-1975 (Offsite-box 22, Folder 3-4)
    - Correspondence. Book Reviews (3 folders), 1966-1974 (Offsite-box 22, Folder 5-7)
      Includes N-YHS's requests of individuals to review select books, the individual's positive or negative response, and transmittal letters of completed reviews. The folders do not hold the reviews or drafts of the reviews.
    - Correspondence. Books Requested for Review (2 folders), 1966-1968 (Offsite-box 22, Folder 8-9)
      Includes requests sent to publishers by N-YHS requesting copies of books to review.
    - Correspondence. Books Requested for Review, 1972-1975 (Offsite-box 23, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence. Permission to Reprint, 1967-1969 (Offsite-box 23, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence. Photographs & Reproductions, 1966-1968 (Offsite-box 23, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence. Promotional Brochure Soliciting Quarterly Articles; Listing in Literary Market Place, 1965 (Offsite-box 23, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence. Publicity, 1968-1970 (Offsite-box 23, Folder 5)
      Includes examples of press notices and publicity for publications other than those of N-YHS as well as some correspondence concerning N-YHS efforts.
    - Correspondence. University Press of Virginia, 1975-1979 (Offsite-box 23, Folder 6)
      Concerns arrangements with the Press to distribute N-YHS publications.
    - Correspondence. Lucius Wilmerding, 1970, 1978 (Offsite-box 23, Folder 7)
      Principally concerns Publications Committee member Wilmerding's review of The Papers of Robert Morris; the folder includes the response of the editors of the Papers to the review.
    - Correspondence. Roger Butterfield, 1964-1969 (Offsite-box 23, Folder 8)
      Includes correspondence with Butterfield principally in his capacity as a member of the Publications Committee (see also the correspondence by author files in subseries II.A) and also regarding his writings for the Quarterly. Includes correspondence of January 1967 from Quarterly readers with compliments on the journal's new design.
    - Correspondence. Publications Committee, 1974, 1978-1979 (Offsite-box 23, Folder 9)
      Includes correspondence and notes with Publications Committee members in 1978-79, including an overview of the objectives and changes related to the "Points of View," "Notes and Documents," "Book Reviews," "Essay Review," and "Briefly Noted" sections of the Quarterly from the late 1960s to 1979, and assessments of various manuscripts submitted for publication. The 1974 item is a clipping.
    - Correspondence. James Heslin, 1976-1977 (Offsite-box 23, Folder 10)
      Includes a small number of notes concerning Quarterly production issues and administrative matters. (See correspondence by author, subseries II.A, for Heslin's comments on manuscripts submitted for publication.)
    - Correspondence. Klaus Gemming (2 folders), 1966-1974 (Offsite-box 23, Folder 11-12)
    - Correspondence. Binding, 1969-1973 (Offsite-box 23, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence. Finn Typographic Service, 1967-1971 (Offsite-box 23, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence. Meriden Gravure (2 folders), 1966-1970 (Offsite-box 23, Folder 15-16)
    - Correspondence. Meriden Gravure (2 folders), 1971-1976 (Offsite-box 24, Folder 1-2)
    - Correspondence. Advertising, 1968-1976 (Offsite-box 24, Folder 3)
      Concerns publishers and book dealers running advertisements in the Quarterly, which began to run such ads in 1972 or 1973.
    - Correspondence. Portrait Catalogue, 1963-1964 (Offsite-box 24, Folder 4)
      Includes notes concerning the possible printing of a revised edition of the Catalogue of American Portraits.
    - Correspondence. Dictionary of Artists in America (3 folders), 1966-1998 (Offsite-box 24, Folder 5-7)
      Includes inquiries, suggested updates and other correspondence received in connection with the DAA. The third folder includes the slips of paper with updates removed from the inscribed copy of the DAA found in Series I.B.
    - Work Files. Publicity Material for N-YHS Books in Print, 1940s-1970s (Offsite-box 24, Folder 8)
      Includes the checklist for the 1961 exhibition John Hill (1770-1850), Master of Aquatint.
    - Work Files. Post Office, 1950s-1970s (Offsite-box 24, Folder 9)
      Includes N-YHS's "Publisher's Statement of Number of Copies" and "Statement of Ownership, Management and Circulation" for various years for the Quarterly, along with various forms, postal rate information, and other matters related to publication mailings.
    - Work Files. Lists for Complimentary Copies of Quarterly, 1966 (Offsite-box 24, Folder 10)
    - Work Files. Budget, 1965-1974 (Offsite-box 25, Folder 1)
      Concerns the costs of design, printing, and other expenses related primarily to the production of the Annual Report and Quarterly.
    - Work Files. Bills (8 folders), 1967-1975 (Offsite-box 25, Folder 2-9)
      Primarily includes bills from Finn Typographic Service, Meriden Gravure Company, and Klaus Gemming.
    - Work Files. Copyright, 1965-1977 (Offsite-box 25, Folder 10)
      Primarily includes photocopies of copyright filings. See also Series I.A for other copyright files for this period.
    - Work Files. Grant Proposal, 1972-1976 (Offsite-box 25, Folder 11)
      Includes general information about grants and a non-NYHS proposal to the NEH for which the Quarterly editor served as a reference.
    - Work Files. Quarterly Subscriber Cards, circa 1968-1980 (Offsite-box 25, Folder 12)
      Includes index cards logging the mailing of the Quarterly to subscribers.
    - Work Files. Book Reviews (11 folders), 1967-1970 (Offsite-box 30, Folder 1-11)
      This set of folders and the next includes the submitted book reviews and review essays, with edits, galley proofs, and other pre-publication preparatory material.
    - Work Files. Book Reviews (8 folders), 1970-1976 (Offsite-box 27, Folder 1-8)
    - Work Files. Index (4 folders), 1968-1972 (Offsite-box 27, Folder 9-12)
      Includes edited versions and galleys of the annual index to the Quarterly.
    - Work Files. Miscellaneous, circa 1974-1976 (Offsite-box 27, Folder 13)
      Includes an edited book review, two sets of captions, and a statement regarding N-YHS publications for the American Bicentennial.
    - Work Files. Manuscript, 1970s? (Offsite-box 27, Folder 14)
      Includes an untitled and unattributed 157 page manuscript concerning New York City history from the colonial period to the end of the nineteenth century.
    - Work Files. Annual Report (9 folders), 1966-1975 (Offsite-box 28, Folder 1-9)
      Includes the edited copy and galleys for the N-YHS annual report. The specific content of the folders varies for each year.
- Series III. Publications (1980s-2000)., 1983-1990, 2000; 5.83 Linear feet
  The bulk of the series is arranged in chronological order by conference year (1983-1988). Within each conference, the material is arranged with the original conference documents, which are principally the presenters' papers, followed by documents related to the later publication based on the conference. The conference documents are followed by a small number of documents concerning other publications.
  The Publications, 1980-2000 series primarily includes documents related to the six annual conferences held at N-YHS from 1983 to 1988 on historical themes and the publications resulting from the first four of these. The series includes all original papers distributed to conference participants and presented there, and it includes documents related to the program planning and logistical arrangements for several of the conferences. The names of the presenters and the titles of their papers are noted in the container list below.
  The series also includes various later versions of the papers as they were prepared for later publication in compilations based on the conference proceedings, as well as other papers not presented at the conferences but included in the publications. The series includes documents concerning the printing, publicity, and other matters related to the production of the conference volumes. The principal correspondence in the series is between N-YHS and William Pencak, the professor of history at Pennsylvania State University who organized the conference programs for N-YHS and who co-edited the subsequent volumes.
  The series includes material related to publicity for the 1987 publication Tales of the Phelps-Dodge Family and minor documents related to Helena Zinkham's guide to N-YHS's Print Room collections and the Perspectives on the Collections of The New-York Historical Society.